Guide to the Susannah Hays Collection of Artwork and Documents, 1992-2016 M1743
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Susannah Hays: artwork and documents
1992-2016
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hays, Susannah
M1743
42 Linear Feet (1 box, 2 cartons, 61 flat boxes)
Collection contains photographs and documents from artist, Susannah Hays.
Biography
Susannah Hays (born, September 12, 1959) is an American artist and educator practicing in the fields of philosophy, contemporary photography and book arts. While she is especially known for her work with cameraless and 19th Century processes, her creative work expands to realms of experimentation in all visual media. She teaches courses that focus on aesthetics in art practice, the embodied mind, constructions of space, topologies, artist’s books and visual autobiography.
Hays was born in Boston Massachusetts and raised in Connecticut where she lived until she moved to the San Francisco Bay Area in 1978 to attend Mills College. She received a BA in Philosophy from Mills, followed by an MFA in Photography from San Francisco Art Institute and an MA in Design from University of California, Berkeley where she continued her PhD Interdisciplinary Studies. While earning her MA, she received the Eisner Prize for Photography. At the Art Institute, she studied with Doug Hall and Ann Chamberlain. At UC Berkeley she studied with philosopher Alva Nöe, poet Lyn Hejinian, painter Tony Dubovsky and filmmaker Trinh T. Minh-ha. In 2012, she moved from Berkeley to Santa Fe, New Mexico where she currently resides.
From 1990 to 2004 Hays was the sole proprietor of Works on Paper, a conservation laboratory preserving works of art, as well as designing and producing artist’s books. In 1996, she curated the national book art exhibition Science Imagined for the Berkeley Art Center. She joined the faculty of the San Francisco Art Institute from 2002-2012 and has also taught at California College of the Art, University of California Berkeley, San Francisco Center for the Book, Shenkar College of Art and Design, Israel, and Leuphana University, Germany. She is currently contributing faculty at Santa Fe University of Art and Design. From 2000 to 2010, she was represented by Scott Nichols Gallery in San Francisco and Donna Seager Gallery in Marin, California. She is presently represented by Photo-Eye Gallery in Santa Fe, New Mexico. Her work has been included in numerous solo and group exhibitions and featured in various articles and reviews such as the New Mexico Museum of Art, Directly from Nature; Scuola Internazionale di Grafica, Verniciatura; None-Such Space, Nature Word ~ Verbe Nature; Townsend Center for the Humanities, Everyday Constellations; and Artists Television Access, Penumbra.
Scope and Content
This collection of her work includes: 8 EGYPT gelatin silver prints -- 1 journal, related to EGYPT --7 SKELLETAL LEAVES prints (6 Vandyke prints, 1 Iris print) -- 1 ONE SUN, ONE APPLE, ONE DAY, framed -- 3 P.O.P. microscope images -- 12 EMPTY BOTTLE SERIES gelatin silver prints -- 1 SEED LEAF gelatin silver photogram -- 2 FALLEN SKY gelatin silver prints -- 6 P.O.P. prints -- 6 EVERYDAY CONSTELLATIONS gelatin silver prints -- 6 PINHOLE VIEWS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO ART INSTITUTE pinhole light drawings -- 3 BETWEEN CEDAR AND VINE gelatin silver prints -- 2 digital images. Also included are the original glass pieces used for the EMPTY BOTTLE series and miscellaneous archival documents, including all the original fragments used for the publication of "Between Cedar and Vine."
Addenda: (accession 2011-143): 1 very large print (14 x 140 inches), 1 framed print, 1 matted photograph, and 2 unframed prints.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2010, 2011, and 2014; gift of Susannah Hays, 2012. Accessions 2010-057, 2011-143, 2012-068, 2014-061, 2014-062, 2014-063, and 2014-064.
Related Archival Materials
Collections (in addition to Stanford University)
The New York Public Library Spencer Collection New York, New York Mills College Library Heller Rare Book Room Oakland, California Museum of Fine Arts Houston, Texas Paul Sack Collection San Francisco, California Santa Barbara Museum of Art Santa Barbara, California Stanford University Cecil H. Green Library Stanford, California University of California Berkeley Environmental Design Library Yale Art Gallery New Haven, Connecticut Yale Haas Book Art Collection New Haven, Connecticut Yale Beinecke Library of American Literature New Haven, Connecticut
Photography.; Women photographers; Hays, Susannah; Hays, Susannah
- Series 1: Glassware
  - Bottles used for "Empty Bottle" photographs [FRAGILE] (Box 1)
  - Bottles used for "Empty Bottle" photographs [FRAGILE] (Box 2)
- Series 2: Photographs
  Scope and Contents
  All items are framed; one framed photograph per box.
  - "Calla Lilly" (Flat-box 3)
  - "Ivy Leaf" (Flat-box 4)
  - "Maple Leaf" (Flat-box 5)
  - "Venus Pencils" (Flat-box 6)
  - "Cross Section Smilax Root" (Flat-box 7)
  - "Triangle Palm Cross Sections" (Flat-box 8)
  - "Ivy Leaf (hearts)" (Flat-box 9)
  - "Nasturium Leaf" (Flat-box 10)
  - "Nest" (Flat-box 11)
  - "Leaf Embryo" (Flat-box 12)
  - "Hope it's not serious..." (Flat-box 13)
  - "One is of the Spirit..." (Flat-box 14)
  - Egypt: color portrait of Susannah Hays taken by Matt Phillips in the Sultan Hannan Masque, 1992 (Flat-box 15, Item 1)
  - Egypt: Pots (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 2)
  - Egypt: Ladder (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 3)
  - Egypt: Girl, Man, and Donkey (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 4)
  - Egypt: Bread for Sale (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 5)
  - Egypt: Mohamed Ali Mosque (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 6)
  - Egypt: Sugarcane (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 7)
  - Egypt: Meeting at the Market (black/white print) (Flat-box 15, Item 8)
  - "Fallen Sky" (1 of 2) (Flat-box 16)
  - "Fallen Sky" (2 of 2) (Flat-box 17)
  - "Seed Leaf" (Flat-box 18)
  - "Cy Twombly" (Flat-box 19)
  - Pinhole Views of the San Francisco Arts Institute (1 of 6) (Flat-box 20)
  - Pinhole Views of the San Francisco Arts Institute (2 of 6) (Flat-box 21)
  - Pinhole Views of the San Francisco Arts Institute (3 of 6) (Flat-box 22)
  - Pinhole Views of the San Francisco Arts Institute (4 of 6) (Flat-box 23)
  - Pinhole Views of the San Francisco Arts Institute (5 of 6) (Flat-box 24)
  - Pinhole Views of the San Francisco Arts Institute (6 of 6) (Flat-box 25)
  - "Street Shadow" (Flat-box 26)
  - "Street Forest" (Flat-box 27)
  - "Map of Changes" (Flat-box 28)
  - "Empty Bottle #1" (Flat-box 39)
  - "Empty Bottle #3" (Bernard Cells) (Flat-box 30)
  - "Empty Bottle #5" (Flat-box 38)
  - "Empty Bottle #6" (Flat-box 33)
  - "Empty Bottle #7" (Flat-box 32)
  - "Empty Bottle #9" (Flat-box 34)
  - "Empty Bottle #10" (Pepsi Pair) (Flat-box 36)
  - "Empty Bottle #11" (Flat-box 31)
  - "Empty Bottle #12" (Flat-box 29)
  - "Empty Bottle #13" (Flat-box 37)
  - "Empty Bottle #14" (Flat-box 35)
  - "Empty Bottle #15" (Balkite) (Flat-box 53)
  - "Eclipse" (Flat-box 40)
  - "Topographic" (Flat-box 41)
  - "Tree/House" (Flat-box 42)
  - "Tree Outside My Window" (Flat-box 43)
  - "Arcata" (Flat-box 44)
  - "Skeletal Leaves - Lace" (1 of 6) (Flat-box 45)
  - "Skeletal Leaves" (2 of 6) (Flat-box 46)
  - "Skeletal Leaves - Forest Map" (3 of 6) (Flat-box 47)
  - "Skeletal Leaves" (4 of 6) (Flat-box 48)
  - "Skeletal Leaves - Eucalyptus" (5 of 6) (Flat-box 49)
  - "Skeletal Leaves - Aspen" (6 of 6) (Flat-box 50)
  - "Skeletal Leaves - Iris print" (Frame 54)
  - Egypt: Pots (framed) (Frame 55)
  - One Sun - One Apple - One Day (Frame 56)
- Series 3: Archival Material
  - Unbound volume: collection of sheets of text pages from "Egypt" (used when exhibiting the book under glass) (Flat-box 51)
  - "Between Cedar and Vine": original fragments (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - "Between Cedar and Vine": original fragments (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - "Between Cedar and Vine": original fragments (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - "Between Cedar and Vine": original publication (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - "Egypt": journal (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - "Egypt": journal (Timeless World) (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - Susannah Hays: early portrait ("portrait of a young artist -- an alter ego at the time") (Box 52, Folder 7)
- Series 4: Accession 2011-143
  - Skeletal leaves: silver-sun prints (2), unframed, 1998 (Items 1)
  - Oak leaf: cyanotype, framed, 1998 (Items 2)
  - Vietnamese girl: gelatin silver print, matted, 1986 (Items 3)
  - One sun - one apple - one day (2 sheets, 14 x 140"), unframed (Items 4)
- Series 5: Accession MSS.2012-068 (Box 1-2)
  The 2012 accession (2 manuscript boxes), includes material from Hays' project, "Science imagined," and exhibition of artists' books held in October, 1996 at the Berkeley Art Center. It also includes 2 audiocassettes of Helen and Newton Harrison: "Meditations on the Sacramento River, the Delta and Bays of San Francisco," 1977, and "Ecological artists: the ecological argument on process, a case for ecosystems as a viable art form," undated (box 2, folder 12).
- Series 6: 2014 Accessions "Pigment Prints" (Flat-box 54)
  The materials consist of four archival pigment prints in one flat box: "Bloodline" taken in Copper Flat, Nevada, 2014; "Nature's writing desk" taken in Osterheide Wald, Germany, 2013; "The Penitente Morada" taken in Abiquiu, New Mexico, 2014; and "Cathedral Forest" taken in Einemhof Forest, Germany, 2013.
- Series 7: 2016 Accessions, 2013-2016
  - Subseries A: Prints from Hays' "Mirror Landscape" series, 2013
    - Mirror Landscape 1 (Flat-box Accn 2016-021 Flat Box 4)
    - Mirror Landscape 2 (Flat-box Accn 2016-021 Flat Box 2)
    - Mirror Landscape 3 (Flat-box Accn 2016-021 Flat Box 3)
    - Mirror Landscape 4 (Flat-box Accn 2016-148 Flat Box 1)
    - Mirror Landscape 5 (Flat-box Accn 2016-044 Flat Box 2)
    - Mirror Landscape 9 (Flat-box Accn 2016-044 Flat Box 1)
    - Mirror Landscape 7 (Flat-box Accn 2016-021 Flat Box 1)
  - Subseries B: Accession 2016-187, 1998-2014
    - Ink Pot, 1999, and Vessel, 1998 (Flat-box Accn 2016-187 Flat Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 4 photogram studies, 1998 (Flat-box Accn 2016-187 Flat Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pinhole San Francisco Art Institute, 2002 (Flat-box Accn 2016-187 Flat Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Santa Rosa de Lima, 2014 (Flat-box Accn 2016-187 Flat Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aquileia Archeological Museum, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-187 Flat Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: Accession 2016-236
    - Concrete ball, 2014 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Isola Madonna del Monte, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Three olive trees, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bones 2, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rock, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Skeletal tree, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Leaning olive tree, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bones, 2013 (Flat-box Accn 2016-236 Flat Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series 8: 2018 Accessions, 2016
  - Moon house, 2016; 5 item(s) (Flat-box Accn 2018-022 Flat Box 1)
    Moon house, 2016, Cedar Mesa, Utah (Bears Ears area); edition 1/15; archival pigment prints on museo silver rag, 17 x 22 inches.
  - Birthing mother, 2016 (Flat-box Accn 2018-022 Flat Box 1)
    Birthing mother, 2016, Rock Canyon, AZ, edition 1/15; archival pigment on museo silver rag, 17 x 22 inches.